Okay, Annette, Leroy, we are very excited to hear more about your program and how CLO
has been used.
So I'm handing over to you.
You can start whenever you are ready.
Okay, thank you, Elaine.
Yes, we are ready.
Okay, so hello, everyone, and today Leroy and I will talk to you about education, our
education in virtual fashion design at our school, the Willem de Kooning Academy in Rotterdam,
the Netherlands.
And first, let me briefly explain how our institute is designed.
So we have students that enter our school in their major.
And there are many major, many design majors to choose from, like this could be graphic
design, this could be advertising, and in our case, this is fashion design.
And to educate our students in skills.
We have our stations, or you could call it also workplaces, such as the print station,
the metal workstation, and the fabric station, or the textile workplace, as you can see here
on the screen.
So all our workplaces and all our stations can be used by all our students.
And that is how we encourage cross-disciplinary work.
And of course, our fashion students, they will be found mostly in the fabric station.
But when we are teaching virtual fashion design, they will be found mostly in the fabric station.
So we need, in fact, the expertise from many stations.
From the fabric station, we need tutors that specialize in patterns and in virtual pattern
making.
From our image and sound station, we need tutors that are skilled in making animations
or games, and who can teach programs like Blender and 3D code.
And in our interaction station, there are people specialized in VR and AR presentations
who teach students how to work in Gravity Sketch.
Or for example, how to print in 3D.
So that is, I think, what makes our school quite unique.
It enables students, after being trained in the necessary basic low 3D skills that are
very much related to fashion and to patterns and fabrics, to explore with these acquired
skills a whole new world of different kinds of mostly interdisciplinary projects in their
own field of interest.
And we have students that explore virtual materials.
And we have students that focus on virtual image making, on fashion in games, or on digital
film.
And we are not just educating for the fashion industry today, but much more for the creative
industry of tomorrow.
Leroy.
Yes, hello.
My name is Leroy, and I'm going to tell a little bit about one of the research projects
that we are conducting around virtual fashion.
Because to keep up with the rapid changing of changes in fashion, we need to focus on
what we are doing in the digital world.
We need to look at the digital world.
We need to look at the digital world as a whole.
But in the context of our creative industry, we as an academy are always looking for new
perspectives and cutting-edge technologies to become a better version of ourselves.
In this light, we have since last year been working on the Erasmus Plus research project
Me, You, Us in collaboration with design school in Kolding in Denmark and University of Ljubljana
in Slovenia.
In this research project, we are searching for new methodologies to educate fashion design,
use in digital tools and virtual reality.
Here in Clo3D is one of our main programs that we use.
However, virtual fashion design is not something new at Willem de Kooning Academy.
We started our virtual journey with Clo3D already back in 2018 when we were introduced to the program at PI Apparel in Berlin.
At that time, we saw that the potential of Clo3D, especially as something practical,
let's say another way of expressing physical design.
However, in recent years, we have been learning together with our students
and have concluded that there's so much more potential in virtual design other than being the extension of physical fashion design.
We came to understand that the virtual design world also needs a virtual design ontology.
In other words, that is a virtual way of understanding the virtual world itself
as well as the physical world around us.
Perhaps it is in our Dutch nature, but it seems very logical to us
that a tool like Clo3D or any other kind of virtual design that matter
could also be used as a critical design tool.
This critical perspective stands also at the core of the ME-US research project.
The research is built up on the three pillars that we call our CIT goals,
which stand for
sustainability, inclusivity and diversity.
Together with these other schools, we are exploring what these urgent themes mean today
and what these themes will mean in the future of virtual fashion design.
As we are still very early research data, as we would like,
but we would love to take you along in our research later on.
Okay, yeah, I'll take it from here again because, yes, today
we really want to share the work of our students,
just then instead of just telling how we do things and how we run things.
So while we are talking, we will show student work.
And for us, creativity and artistic development of our students takes center stage,
and therefore we do not just focus on the technical advances of the program Clo3D,
but rather on its creative potential.
And to be clear, we, the Willem de Kooning Academy,
is not a fashion institute.
So we do not feel obliged to educate ready to go fashion professionals
that will all inevitably work in the current fashion industry.
Of course, they might choose to do so, and we support them in that too, of course.
But that is not our full intention.
We are an art school that trains fully rounded creatives
that might later in life become a fashion designer.
So for us, a good student knows how to use their creativity
to set action in motion,
and to use design as a means to tell a story,
to be critical to the world around them,
and to be a part of the solution rather than the problem.
Therefore, we train them to, well, firstly to work sufficiently in Clo3D
to visualize their designs,
but also at the same time we challenge them to hack the program
and use Clo3D to challenge society's notions of fashion.
And this is very exciting to us.
It might be our rebellious Dutch nature,
but we like to challenge the parameters of systems
and to disturb existing hierarchies
and to see what lays beyond the known.
To us, it is a system embedded in fashion
to challenge the current state of fashion.
And in order to do so, we have embedded Clo3D
in three of the four years of our fashion bachelor course
with a possible fourth year,
when a student chooses to use Clo3D for their graduation project.
And just like any other fashion course that uses Clo3D in its curriculum,
we acknowledge that there is still a great gap
between physical making and the use of virtual prototyping.
So Leroy is one of the professors who uses Clo3D in his classes
and who encounters this discrepancy in his classes.
Leroy, could you tell a little bit more
how you try to bring the physical making
and the virtual making together in your classes?
Well, thank you, Annette.
I will try to do so.
It is indeed true that one of the biggest problems
that we face in our education
is this shift towards virtual and digital design
in our education curriculum
was the gap between physical and virtual making.
From an outside perspective,
this gap might seem insignificant,
but it poses a real problem
and a headbreaker for us as a department.
To be fully honest,
we are still searching for answers
and I cannot provide a full answer today.
That's also why we do this research project.
But I can say this.
From our experience,
we have learned that the divide
between physical and virtual making
is not just a question of technology
that can be solved by one of the many features
of the Clo3D program.
For example,
students can easily create patterns in Clo3D
and print them in order to stitch their digital sites
in physical samples.
This is very easy for them.
This is not the problem,
but the actual problem lays much deeper
in the inner world of the students' creativity
and design intuition.
Over the years,
we have noticed that Clo3D was often seen
as an additional skill next to their physical design practice.
We still see that there is still a lot of skepticism
from a more traditional corner of our fashion industry.
Virtual making was just another way
of expressing physical fashion design.
We also still see these attitudes towards virtual design
in many fashion institutes.
Virtual design is just in many cases
a kind of add-on in education,
kind of a nice way
to present a physical dress
that you could make for real.
On the other side,
as an academy,
we see that the next generation
who grew up with the technology
is able to use tech already
as their second nature.
In the Netherlands today,
a six-year-old child often knows
how to use a tablet
before they know how to write.
The future is clearly already here.
At the Wim de Kooning Academy,
we feel the need to respond to the need
to respond to this rapidly changing world.
Therefore, we have chosen to include
virtual and digital communication
in the basics of our fashion major education,
right next to physical skills.
By simultaneously teaching students
practical skills like pattern drawing
in physical and virtual reality,
we hope to annul this divide altogether
by creating a parallel design intuition.
We hope,
by continuously switching back and forth
between physical and virtual reality,
that students no longer feel this division,
but rather see them
as an extension of one another.
One and the same thing.
Well, that's what we hope.
Annette will now tell you
how we do this
in the first year design assignment
called Bending for Functionality.
And whilst I was having this talk,
you can see the work
of one of our students
called Besa Demirci.
Thanks.
I think so.
Now back to you.
From the very first day
that our students entered
the fashion department,
we introduced them to the idea
of virtual technology.
And for a matter of fact,
we have heard from students
that they really choose for our school
for its virtual and digital approach
to fashion.
As we said,
our major fashion design education
is roughly three years,
and we introduce virtual fashion mythologies
in block 1.3.
So that is in the first year,
just before the summer holiday.
And of course,
we do introduce digital technical skills
like pattern drawing
and the basics of clothes
with the earlier on in the year.
But to guarantee
an inclusive learning environment,
we must presume that students
still need to learn all these skills,
even though they might already
be very experienced
in virtual pattern drawing.
And as we mentioned before,
these practical skills are taught
at our school
by our station instructors.
And so for the first year students,
these are Paulina Martina,
who has a background
in speculative VR design
and is an expert on AI.
And Geert van der Meer,
who is a professional pattern drawing
with a great knowledge
of digitizing patterns.
So when our students know
the basics of both the physical
and the virtual fashion design,
our fashion design tutors come in.
For the banding functionality project,
these are Selina Parr and Anouk van Klaveren.
And together,
they will introduce our students
to this parallel methodology
of designing fashions.
So the focus of our first year project
is that students learn
to critically question
the function of everyday garments.
And this research,
they start in the physical realm
with Selina Parr
and in Cloth3D with Anouk van Klaveren.
In the physical starting class,
they start with dissecting an iconic garment
and questioning its functionality
through physical methods.
This could be through draping with the garment,
cutting it up, making collages,
sketching on paper,
just physical ways of expressing a design.
And then also quite traditionally,
they sample this garment in Calico
for which they will have to make
the pattern by hand on paper.
And only then they will digitize
the paper and patterns into Cloth3D
and make a 3D render of their design.
Because there is also a physical Calico sample
at that time,
the tutors can really compare
this virtual 3D model
to its physical Calico counterparts.
And this provides the tutors
and the instructors with an actual reference
to measure the 3D garment too.
Okay, while this is all happening
at the same time,
as Selina's classes go on.
In Anouk's classes,
students start with a virtual garment
that they morph and dissect and transform
with the tools in Cloth3D.
We try to cultivate the same curiosity
and spontaneity in virtual space
as our students also have
in the physical assignments.
Although students are playing around
with patterns in the 2D box of Cloth3D,
physical makeability is not a concern to us
in this virtual exploratory phase.
Students first need to visualize
their ideas in virtual space.
And then in the second half
of the semester,
they will adapt these virtual designs
into makeable patterns
that can be printed and executed in fabric.
So with one tutor,
the students go from physical to virtual.
And with the other tutor,
they go from virtual to physical.
And these processes,
they run parallel.
So at any given point in this project,
they are doing each segment,
both in physical space
and in virtual space at the same time.
And then I will continue for year two.
The second year project
called Future of Fashion.
And I have a few videos
that I will show in the meantime
because they are working on animations.
The second year project
called Future of Fashion
primarily focuses on the power
of speculation in fashion design
and virtual fashion design
as a device for storytelling.
The brief to our students is quite simple.
Come up with a future scenario
of the world
and design a virtual collection
that represents the speculative scenario.
The final project
of Future of Fashion project
is an animation showcasing
this digital collection
in a self-created virtual environment.
Here we see the work of Zala Meshan.
Guiding this project
are Sreena Par.
And I go now to the next video.
Yes.
Guiding this project
are Sreena Par
on the collection design front.
And Esther van Brake
who is actually an alumni
from Willem de Kooning
who already in 2017
graduated herself
with a virtual fashion project.
She now teaches concept development
and Natalia van Coren
who will focus on circular economies
and sustainability in this project.
What we hope to do in this project
is not only focus on the problems
of the world today,
which is quite easily,
you only have to kind of look outside to see it,
but we ask the students
to speculate about the problems of tomorrow
from the perspective of today.
For some students,
this means that they try to come up
with a solution-driven concept
to battle the impact of problems
such as rising sea levels
or reducing biodiversity.
However, other students
use this Future of Fashion project
as a platform for social commentary,
through grotesque exaggeration and humor,
designing a parody of contemporary culture.
For example, here we see
the project of Philip Malmgren
who really kind of explores the parameters
and the limitations of the Closed2D program
through making kind of a parody out of it.
On a more practical skill-based level,
we want to teach our students
how to seamlessly switch
between different software and methods
of making digital images.
Again, we want to cultivate
a digital intuition in our students
and provide different ways
of making digital images contribute to this.
For example, students design
and make their clothes in Closed2D.
They create environments
and those virtual worlds in Blender,
but also they sculpt accessories
in graffiti sketch or Rhino.
And in the end,
use a multitude of different engines
to make their animation videos
come to life.
This, of course,
is all highly technical
and goes somewhat beyond
the technical capabilities
of our fashion tutors.
Also, my technical capabilities.
But at Willem de Koon Academy,
we are very lucky to have stations
where there is plenty of expert knowledge
on Closed2D programming
and virtual design methods.
For this project,
we work closely with
the Image and Sound Station.
This is represented by Peter Schropp,
who specializes in animations and games,
and with the Interaction Station
represented by Brigitte Lichtenegger,
Joris Butter and Mike Pelletier,
all experts in AR, VR,
and interaction design.
Yeah, so last part
is in fact the year three part.
The last real assignment
in our fashion design major
we call the major assignment,
partially due to its enormous size,
but also because all the knowledge
that the students have obtained
so far accumulates in this project.
And it is also the moment
that students really have to start
thinking about professionalization
in preparation for their internships
the second half of the third year.
So we believe that with professionalization
comes a great degree of specialization.
And we acknowledge that our program
can be very demanding for our students.
And therefore,
we ask them to choose
either a physical track
in which they will focus
on making a physical collection
or a virtual track
in which they will work
on an immersive virtual fashion experience.
And by this time,
students already know much better
what their strengths are.
And we see that they quite naturally
choose for their own preference.
The choice to split the course
into physical and virtual is because
we believe that in this year
of professionalization,
it should be up to the student
to choose what they want to specialize in.
And by this time,
the station classes have become
so incredibly expert
that we acknowledge
that they are only useful
for those who really want to continue
in virtual fashion design.
However, we see an increasing demand
and interest in our students
with our students
to follow these classes.
And although we make it
a division between physical
and virtual projects,
these two tracks,
they really start off together
in an extensive conceptual phase.
As we said before,
we believe that the design process
of physical and virtual fashion
is the same.
They only diverge
in a technical execution.
The fashion tutors
that are assigned to this project
are Leroy van Halen,
who's sitting next to me here,
and who, next to teaching,
also works as a teacher
as a fashion designer
for Parisian luxury brands.
And there is Anouk van Klaveren,
who also has an experimental
fashion-based practice
that focuses on exhibitions
and fashion in the public context.
Yes, thank you, Annette.
Yes, you saw a few examples
of projects that we did.
And as I said,
we really kind of wanted to make,
well, in this assignment,
we do very kind of expert,
immersive virtual fashion experiences.
And we want to kind of show you
all one particular project.
This project is from Nino van Litt.
And Nino van Litt is a student of us
that really manages to very well
come up with a very unique perspective
of what he wants
and uses all different kinds of platforms
to make, in the end,
he made a game.
But he made the clothes,
which are very speculative clothes.
He made the garments,
for example, in Cloth3D.
And then he, well, first of all,
he started off already kind of digital
by using a lot of digital materials.
His collection is, in the end,
about stock image
and digital material culture
that he then kind of imported
into designs of made in Cloth3D.
And then he used lots of different
engines and programs,
but predominantly Unity
to make a playable game out of it.
We are going to show you
a little video about,
well, of his game.
And in the corner,
you see the student himself.
Hey, what's up, guys?
It's Scarce here.
And today, I hope you're doing well.
And it's time for a reaction
to an interesting post,
a thought piece that I saw
on the internet on our subreddit.
Huge holidays.
Look it up.
Chris, where are you going?
Oh, my God.
What is going on?
Going to take a few hours to get 20K?
Oh, you bet your ass it will, yeah.
Adequate for 20K.
That's a bad guy.
When he comes into my shop,
he causes trouble.
Rolling 80 of these
is going to be the biggest
fucking pain in the ass.
Oh, my God.
Yeah, baby.
That's what I've been waiting for.
That's what it's all about.
So here you can really see
what we like to show to our students.
Of course, Clos3D at our academy,
yes, it starts very much off
where you saw kind of expression of design,
but also there are so many more opportunities
in a much more creative sense
to use this program.
And all the garments that you saw
and kind of the statues in this gallery space,
they were all created in Clos3D,
but then only using this program
as a segment in a much bigger creative process.
Thanks, Leroy.
And thank you all for listening.
At Willem de Kooning Academy,
our aim is to break down the digital divide,
and we have entered a digital reality.
And at WDKA, we are in this together.
So in our Erasmus project,
Me, You, Us, the research project,
we research the interaction
between the physical and the virtual,
the old and the new skills,
the traditions and the possible futures.
So I hope all the students
work that passed in the last half hour
has inspired you.
It sure keeps inspiring us.
Thank you.